Several improvements to the original Deep Q-Learning algorithm have been suggested.
该论文提供了多个针对原始深度 Q 学习算法的改进建议
We look at three of the more prominent ones,
我们来看看其中三个最重要的改进
Double DQNs, Prioritized Replay and Dueling Networks.
双 DQN 优先回放和对抗网络
The first problem we are going to address is
我们要解决的第一个问题是
the overestimation of action values that Q-Learning is prone to.
Q 学习容易出现的过高估计动作值问题
Let's look back at the update rule for
我们来回顾下具有函数逼近的
Q-Learning with function approximation and focus on the TD target.
Q 学习更新规则 并重点看看 TD 目标
Here the max operation is necessary
这里的 max 运算有必要用到
to find the best possible value we could get from the next state.
以便计算可以从下个状态获得的最佳潜在值
To understand this better,
为了很好地理解这一点
let's rewrite the target and expand the max operation.
我们重写目标并展开 max 运算
It is just a more efficient way of saying that we want to obtain the Q-value for
可以更有效地理解为
the state S prime and the action that results in
我们想要获得状态 S′ 的 Q 值
the maximum Q-value among all possible actions from that state.
以及从该状态的所有潜在动作中实现最大 Q 值的动作
When we write it this way,
写成这样时
we can see that it's possible for the arg max operation to make a mistake,
可以看出 arg max 运算有可能会出错
especially in the early stages.
尤其是在早期阶段
Why? Because the Q-values are still evolving and we may
为何？因为 Q 值依然在变化
not have gathered enough information to figure out the best action.
我们可能没有收集足够的信息来判断最佳动作是什么
The accuracy of our Q-values depends a lot on
Q 值的准确性在很大程度上取决于
what actions have been tried and what neighboring states have been explored.
尝试了哪些动作以及探索了哪些周围的状态
In fact, it has been shown that this results in an overestimation of Q-values
实际上 事实证明这一部分会导致过高估计 Q 值
since we always pick the maximum among a set of noisy numbers.
因为我们始终在一组杂乱数字中选择最大值
So, maybe we shouldn't blindly trust these values.
或许我们不应该盲目地信任这些值
What can we do to make our estimation more robust?
如何使我们的估算更可靠？
One idea that has been shown to work very well in practice is called Double Q-Learning.
有一个经实践证明效果很好的方法是双 Q 学习
Where we select the best action using one set of parameters,
我们使用一组参数 w 选择最佳动作
W, but evaluate it using a different set of parameters W prime.
但是使用另一组参数 w′ 评估动作
It's basically like having
相当于有两个单独的函数逼近器
two separate function approximaters that must agree on the best action.
它们必须在最佳动作上达成一致
If W picks an action that is not the best according to W prime,
如果根据 W′ W 选择的动作并不是最佳动作
then the Q-value returned is not that high.
那么返回的 Q 值不会那么高
In the long run, this prevents the algorithm from propagating
长期下来 可以避免该算法
incidental higher rewards that may have been obtained
传播偶尔获得的更高奖励
by chance and don't reflect long term returns.
这些奖励并不能反映长期回报
Now, you may be thinking,
你可能会问
where do we get this second set of parameters from?
我们从哪获得第二组参数？
In the original formulation of Double Q-Learning,
在原始的双 Q 学习公式中
you would basically maintain two value functions and randomly choose one of
你会保留两个值函数 在每一步随机地选择一个函数进行更新
them to update at each step using the other only for evaluating actions.
并仅使用另一个评估动作
But when using DQNs with fixed Q targets,
但是将 DQN 与固定 Q 目标结合使用时
we already have an alternate set of parameters.
我们已经有一组替代的参数
Remember W minus.
还记得 W- 吗？
It turns out that since W minus is kept frozen for a while it is different enough
实际上 W- 已经保留不用有一段时间了
from W that it can be reused for this purpose, and that's it.
它与 W 之间的区别已经足够大 可以重新用于该目的 原理就是这样
This simple modification keeps Q-values in check,
这个简单的修改可以使 Q 值变得可靠起来
preventing them from exploding in the early stages of learning or fluctuating later on.
防止它们在学习的早期阶段爆发或在后期阶段出现波动
The resulting policies have also been shown to perform significantly
经证明 形成的策略效果
better than Vanilla DQNs. All right.
比 Vanilla DQN 强很多
The next issue we'll look at is related to experience replay.
我们要讨论的下个问题与经验回放有关
Recall the basic idea behind it.
回忆下经验回放的基本原理
We interact with the environment to collect experience tuples,
我们与环境互动以便收集经验元组
save them in a buffer and then later we randomly sample a batch to learn from.
将元组保存在缓冲区 然后随机抽取一个批次以从中学习规律
This helps us break the correlation between
这样有助于打破连续经验之间的关系
consecutive experiences and stabilizes our learning algorithm.
并使学习算法稳定下来
So far so good,
到目前为止 没什么问题
but some of these experiences may be more important for learning than others.
但是某些经验可能比其他经验更重要 更需要学习
Moreover, these important experiences might occur infrequently.
此外 这些重要的经验可能很少发生
If we sample the batch as uniformly then
如果我们均匀地按批次抽样
these experiences have a very small chance of getting selected.
那么这些经验被选中的概率很小
And since buffers are practically limited in capacity,
因为缓冲区实际上容量有限
older important experiences may get lost.
因此更早的重要经验可能会丢失
This is where the idea of prioritized experience replay comes in.
这时候就要用到优先经验回放了
But what criteria should we use to assign priorities to each tuple?
但是我们根据什么条件来为每个元组分配优先级呢？
One approach is to use the TD error delta.
一种方法是使用 TD 误差增量
The bigger the error,
误差越大
the more we expect to learn from that tuple.
我们从该元组中预计学到的规律就越多
So let's take the magnitude of this error as a measure of priority
我们将此误差的大小作为衡量优先级的条件
and store it along with each corresponding tuple in the replay buffer.
并将其与每个相应的元组一起存储在回放缓冲区
When creating batches, we can use this value to compute a sampling probability,
在创建批次时 我们可以使用该值计算抽样概率
select any tuple i with a probability equal to its priority value Pi,
选择任何元组 i 的概率等于其优先级值 pi
normalized by the sum of all priority values in the replay buffer.
并用回放缓冲区中的所有优先级值之和标准化
And when a tuple is picked,
选择某个元组后
we can update its priority with a newly computed TD error using the latest Q-values.
我们可以使用最新的 Q 值将其优先级更新为新计算的 TD 误差
This seems to work fairly well and has been shown to
似乎效果不错
reduce the number of batch updates needed to learn a value function.
经证明 可以减少学习值函数所需的批次更新数量
There are a couple of things we can improve.
有几个方面可以加以改进
First, note that if the TD error is zero,
首先 如果 TD 误差为 0
then the priority value of the tuple and
那么该元组的优先级值
hence its probability of being picked will also be zero.
及其被选中的概率也为 0
Zero or very low TD error doesn't
0 或非常低的 TD 误差
necessarily mean we have nothing more to learn from such a tuple.
并不一定就表明我们从此类元组中学不到任何规律
It might be the case that our estimate was
可能是因为到该时间点为止
close due to the limited samples we visited till that point.
经历的样本有限 估值很接近真实的值
So, to prevent such tuples from being starved for selection,
为了防止此类元组不被选中
we can add a small constant e to every parity value.
我们可以在每个平衡值后面加上一个很小的常量 e
Another issue along similar lines is that greedily using this priority values may lead to
另一个类似的问题是贪婪地使用这些优先级值
a small subset of experiences being replayed over and
可能会导致一小部分经验子集不断被回放
over resulting in a sort of over-fitting to that subset.
导致对该子集的过拟合
To avoid this, we can reintroduce some element of uniform random sampling.
为了避免该问题 我们可以重新引入一些均匀随机抽样元素
This adds another hyper parameter a,
这样会添加另一个超参数 a
which we use to redefine the sampling probability as priority Pi,
我们用它将抽样概率重新定义为
to the power of a divided by the sum of all priorities,
优先级 pi 的 a 次幂除以所有优先级之和 pk
Pk, each raised to the power a.
每个都是 a 次幂
We can control how much we want to use
我们可以通过调整该参数
priority versus randomness by varying this parameter.
控制采用优先级与随机性的幅度
Where a equals zero,
a 等于 0 表示采用完全均匀随机性方法
corresponds to pure uniform randomness and a equals one, only uses priorities.
a 等于 1 表示仅采用优先级值
When we use prioritized experience replay,
当我们使用优先经验回放时
we have to make one adjustment to our update rule.
我们需要对更新规则进行一项调整
Remember that our original Q-Learning update is
我们的原始 Q 学习更新
derived from an expectation over all experiences.
来自于对所有经验的预期结果
When using a stochastic update rule,
在使用随机性更新规则时
the way we sample these experiences
我们对这些经验抽样的方式
must match the underlying distribution they came from.
必须与来源底层分布匹配
This is preserved when we sample experienced tuples uniformly from the replay buffer.
当我们从回放缓冲区均匀地抽样经验元组时 能够满足这一前提条件
But this assumption is violated when we use
但是当我们采用非均匀抽样（例如使用优先级）时
a non-uniform sampling for example using priorities.
则不满足该前提条件
The Q-values we learn will be biased according to
我们学习的 Q 值将因为这些优先级值出现偏差
these priority values which we only wanted to use for sampling.
我们只希望使用这些值进行抽样
To correct for this bias,
为了更正这一偏差
we need to introduce an important sampling weight equal to one over n,
我们需要引入一个重要的抽样权重 等于 1/N
where n is the size of this replay buffer,
N 是该回放缓冲区的大小
times one over the sampling probability, Pi.
乘以 1/p(i) p(i) 是抽样概率
We can add another hyper parameter, b,
我们可以添加另一个超参数 b
and raise each important sampling weight to b,
并将每个重要抽样权重提升为 b
to control how much these weights affect learning.
控制这些权重对学习的影响程度
In fact, these weights are more important towards the end of learning when
实际上 这些权重在学习结束时更加重要
your Q-values begin to converge so you can increase b from a low value to one over time.
这时候 Q 值开始收敛 因此你可以逐渐将 b 从很低的值增加到 1
Again, these details may be hard to understand at first,
这些细节部分可能一开始很难明白
but each small improvement can contribute
但是每个小小的改进
a lot towards more stable and efficient learning.
都可以有效地达到更加稳定高效的学习算法
So make sure you give the prioritized experience replay paper a good read.
因此确保仔细阅读优先经验回放论文
The final enhancement of DQNs that we'll briefly
我们将简单介绍最后一个 DQN 增强技巧
look at is appropriately titled, Dueling Networks.
叫做对抗网络 名称很好懂
Here is a typical DQN architecture.
这是一个典型 DQN 架构
A sequence of convolutional layers followed by
有一系列卷积层
a couple of fully connected layers that produce Q-values.
然后是几个完全连接层 生成了 Q 值
The core idea of Dueling Networks is to use two streams.
对抗网络的核心概念是使用两个信息流
One that estimates the state value function,
一个估算状态值函数
and one that estimates the advantage for each action.
一个估算每个动作的优势
These streams may share some layers in the beginning such as convolutional layers,
这两个信息流可能在一开始具有一些共同的层级 例如卷积层
then branch off with their own fully connected layers,
然后分支为各自的完全连接层
and finally the desired Q-values are
最后通过结合状态和优势值
obtained by combining the state and advantage values.
获得期望的 Q 值
The intuition behind this is that the value of
这么做的原因是
most states don't vary a lot across actions.
大部分状态在动作之间变化不大
So it makes sense to try and directly estimate them.
因此可以尝试直接估算它们
But we still need to capture the difference actions make in each state.
但是我们依然需要捕获动作在每个状态中产生的区别
This is where the advantage function comes in.
这时候就要用到优势函数
Some modifications are necessary to adapt Q-Learning to this architecture,
需要进行一些调整 以便将 Q 学习应用于该架构
which you can find in the Dueling networks paper.
你可以在对抗网络论文中找到该调整方法
Along with double DQNs and prioritized replay,
和双 DQN 以及经验回放一样
this technique has resulted in significant improvement over vanilla DQNs.
该技巧显著改善了 vanilla DQN